all right hello and welcome it's January
17th
2025 and we're in active inference guest
stream
96.1 with Ron Edelman discussing
designing intelligent experiences for
trust so thank you Ron for joining and
looking forward to your presentation and
the
discussion all right so really happy to
be here um I must say that I'm only here
because I randomly reached out to Carl
and he was very kind and generous and
he decided to uh you know ENT entertain
um some conversations and those this has
been about two years um those
conversations led to a couple
presentations meeting some really uh
incredible people uh involved in active
inference and it really kind of set me
on a new course new ways of
thinking and I wanted to share a more
practical perhaps implementation
practitioner approach to what are the
real world problems we're seeing with
integrating the brilliant community of
you know people who are trained in
basian statistics um is a completely
different way to think about problem
solving and if you start working with
product managers with designers um
business folks they might have just a
very different framework for thinking
about how to create
systems and I I just want to kind of
share an experience I had which kind of
changed my life and it was about
music and I was really struggling to
learn the western style of music and I
had a teacher who studied in India and
so they have a different way it's
instead of writing things down in
straight lines and you you sing your
music first it's called kocol so um
quarter notes would be tuad tuad tuad
tuad right triplets would be tu tu tu tu
tu
and that
system of learning accelerated me more
than in a few weeks than years of like
taking music
lessons
and the reason that this I think is
important is because it introduced me to
the idea around having a trusted source
of Truth and
collaboration all of a sudden when I was
playing music we could all agree you
know metronomes timing it opened up an
entire language for me for how to
interface with others be completely
creative have that freedom to
collaborate but it was also safe right
like it was also we could remain within
the constraints of the system and and
that unlocked all kinds of incredible
learning experiences for me and since
then I've viewed information flowing
through organizational networks kind of
through the lens of music like what is
our metronome that allows us to
collaborate when we're building software
when we're providing recommendations to
customers um when we're troubleshooting
operational and business processes
and I think uh Carl enjoyed my analogy
of synchronization and music when
talking about these systems so he called
it computational Psychiatry uh not words
I would use but that's that's how this
journey kind of began for me so just a
little bit about me I've uh written two
books now the first one was came out
last year it's unifying business data
and code um it was it was incredible to
WR in a Riley book um and that book deal
got me a second book deal the language
of innovation which is coming out in a
couple of months and my life has been
around meeting like incredibly talented
people and figuring how do we leverage
uh that creative brain power uh and
passion and help
organizations minimize their costs
and I think that uh I view myself as
kind of kind of a bridge a connector
between all these different um worlds
and unifying business data and code was
kind of my first exploration into how we
formalize um methodologies to get
everyone to have quote unquote a
metronome
so how did I we get to this to the idea
of like why is trust interesting well it
started with a conversation with Carl I
think um theoretical neurobiology group
um where I asked what is the definition
of understanding and he was like well
it's quite simply it's the the uh it's a
shared model right if you both have the
same inputs you should both have the
same outputs and that for me was how I
connected back to to the idea of the
metronome
um because in reality we don't have
shared met nums in a business in in fact
I would say if you go to two different
departments and you say what does this
word mean usually they will give me a
different
definition and even if I ask two people
within the same department just as a
pure Consulting kind of approach on you
know process optimization and
architecture explain to me how this
process works it is almost never
described to me the
same so this is a really hard hard
problem because if we're going to be
able to have you know AI make decisions
and people can't even agree on what the
the operational reality is how is an AI
going to do
that
so the metronome for
me is just a symbol of it's always
something I could trust it it was just
something I could like let go of holding
on to what I think is right and I'm just
this is the truth and everyone else can
align around it
and it was really interesting for me to
approach the problem like how would you
computationally define it and I I will
tell you I do not have a computational
definition of trust right now but I am
thinking about
Frameworks approaches uh ways to
Quantified engineer trust in systems and
this to me is a very very exciting
problem
so the the best analogy I had was when I
was just I was feeling a little tired
and I started you know watching watching
uh some TV and I I pull up the mie movie
Edge of Tomorrow um for those of you
that don't know Edge of Tomorrow it's
like it's Groundhog Day meets sci-fi um
Tom Cruz keeps dying over and over in
this battle with aliens and each time he
would wakes up he's learned from his
previous
experiences but there's one scene in the
um in the movie which really kind of
helped me think of ways to
articulate ways we can think about trust
so in the beginning Tom's like smiling
he's laughing you know 100% feeling
safety and control the general says
you're going to go out into the
battlefield and he's a Tom Cruz is a
reporter you're going to report on the
um on the on the war Tom's afraid of
this and so he threatens the the general
if you send me into battle I'm gonna
basically make you look bad um and so
then the general then says I'm gonna
call you a deserter and he throws Tom
not into a reporter role but actually
into this you know mechanized combat
suit um and Tom doesn't even know how to
use the suit and eventually the the uh
Sergeant says jump or die and it's in
this particular moment where it's like
the opposite of trust kind
of felt clear to me right he has no
certainty of what's going to happen it's
pure chaos he has no control over these
events he has no safety because he's
he's gonna die possibly and you know he
has no understanding of like what the
heck is even happening to me
and and if we look back at how
llms and not everything is llms but llms
seem to be very hot and but I think this
is true in in for any kind of machine
Learning probabilistic System when we
are in situations granted it's not the
Edge of Tomorrow that situations but
when we are in a situation where we have
to make decisions that could be life or
death it could be patient care it could
be the life or death of a company if you
make a wrong decision um it could be the
difference between layoffs
right when we use these probabilistic
systems um and we're leaving the
deterministic
approach we have a
class because there's a lot of attention
on you know fine-tuning and prompt
engineering and you know trying to force
these AI systems to behave
deterministically but they are not
deterministic and um so I want to I want
to think about these four dimensions
around certainty control safety and
understanding right
so when we have what's if you're
familiar with the paper called tool
former
um it introduces these kind of two terms
postprocessing and and pre-processing
and so what open AI did when they
first kind of shaped the entire industry
right that we that we now are thinking
about it's you give us all of your you
know put everything in a vector database
H you send you do your fine-tuning your
prompt engineering and you know our AI
is going to be super in you know quote
unquote super intelligent generally
intelligence
um it's really good if that's your
business model to have companies do that
right it's in their benefit it's in the
cloud provider's benefit for a business
to have really messy
data um and of and of course
preprocessing is hard because you can't
possibly know in advance all the ways
things will be used and all the
rules and
we're left with this kind of blackbox
situation and it leaves uh this black
box situation obviously is very
ambiguous right and when we're going
shopping and we want to buy a cup of
coffee we don't want to have a
probabilistic answer to what a a cup of
coffee
costs we we want to
know this is how much it costs every
single time when we're going to make our
decision right and so how do we bring in
um these probabilistic and deterministic
systems into user
experiences um another
dimension around safety compliance this
typically governance kind of things is
just sharing my experience F first of
all if you're into if you're a
taxonomist or you know if your if your
um knowledge graphs and linked data are
your thing incredibly powerful great but
I do want to share with people what the
problems I see from in the real world
companies that are trying to implement
these
approaches uh you have a very small
group of people who cannot possibly know
everything in the company and every
operation and Define things so they
become quickly become bottlenecks for
these top- down rules and the bottom up
quests become an overwhelming
tsunami so people just go around it and
now you have the worst of of these
worlds right because you're paying for
enterprise software that you're also not
using and you have all this like Shadow
you know Shadow it kind of things going
on
and when we you know thinking of biology
like when ants leave these trails
we typically have a really hard time
leaving trails of how we solve
tasks but if we can find a way to leave
trails these audit Trails of how do we
solve cognitive
tasks we we create the opportunity for
kind of an organizational scale learning
right
so the difference between the top down
apprach approach and this complex
adaptive systems approach is if you just
can observe how people are solving
tasks you will you will have a fluid way
to see what are the rules and processes
people are following in the real
world um autonomously with freedom etc
etc and how do those how how are the
interactions with governance and this is
this is what um was the origin of what I
was really interested in working
on so
um I had a previous startup where it we
basically um pulled dat all public data
from GitHub if you're a developer and
you did some code we had data on you and
your code and down to the commit level
and we were trying to sell it to
recruiters like hey do you want develop
velers we can analyze people's codes and
recommend Developers for you to
recruit uh but I had a problem I had two
weeks for a big demo to like you know
one of these Fortune 50 companies and we
our all our data was in a SQL database
and I wanted to use Ai and I didn't have
time to learn Lang chain and um you know
figure out how to convert things into a
vector database I had to hack something
together which would enable
me to use natural language to query a
database and so I decided to take a
really old school approach just using
regular
expressions and that
is what I'm trying to formalize into a
protocol which I call Trust
Loop um so before I go into anything
Daniel is are there any questions coming
up or any comments or should I proceed
not yet
pered thanks very great
so we want to take these kind of four
dimensions and just think about them in
in terms of how we're designing systems
where people can learn and then the
whole organization can learn and where I
think that could be really interesting
is you know uh someone responded as I
started posting about this about the EU
AI act
um you know how are you going to be
compliant and I think this particular
protocol has a lot of Promise around uh
compliance because everything is meant
to be open and transparent and with
trails and I'm I'm trying to bridge them
together bring in some reinforcement
learning principles some active
inference principles but that is kind of
what is what is guiding my Approach so
what does the architecture look
like um first of all we need to
integrate into
a user
interface and then we need to be able to
have a registry of
rules the approach I took is to have an
llm look at my
rules and then recommend
suggestions to dynamically um
improve with a feedback loop any kind of
rule management for me as an individual
but it could also for a system if there
are like compliance or regulatory
requirements and then uh lastly is this
kind of cognitive audit Trail right so
I'm going to give you a very super
simple
example
um but let's say I and this is literally
the most simple example I could come up
with but let's say for example I have
this chat interface and I want to ask a
question about my data right like let's
say have some data set or database and I
want to calculate Revenue so like if I
were to post a question you know can you
tell me uh what my Revenue was um etc
etc and they're clearly some bugs um
simply asking up here a feedback loop
well what do you mean by Revenue do you
mean net or gross because these are
wildely different
calculations this is incredibly
incredibly
simple it is merely identifying possible
ambiguity in my
language and then saying hey is this
what you
mean or hey do you want to use the
revenue calculation from this particular
database now why is this
important well let's go um let's go back
to this slide
here because I I think the important
question is why use AI at
all if you can
accomplish your
task in the most efficient manner that
doesn't mean there needs to be AI
involved so
there was a really interesting metric
from uh versus recently which I know
everyone here is a fan of that it beat
open ai's Mastermind um um gameplay
versus 01 I think the 01 model and it
said uh 01 I think it was like took five
hours and cost $200 and was only 70%
accurate and versus was 100% accurate
took 5 seconds and like cost 50 cents
that's amazing I love that I love that
and this is no disrespect to versus or
anyone in AI but my immediate question
was hang on a second I'm pretty sure the
algorithm to solve
Mastermind exists in a Javascript file
somewhere on
GitHub and that means zero cost and in
instead of taking seconds it's
milliseconds and 100%
accurate actually check it was python
code is the code I checked but same
thing right and so it just kind of
reinforced this idea
around hey the whole industry is
barreling at 100 miles an hour towards
this post uh sorry this
postprocessing
Paradigm but
why why should we send everything
through a
how do we know what we should send
through Ai and what we should not send
through
Ai and so
um that is what the trustly protocol is
meant to do is we're we're trying to
figure out how do we
route which types of cognitive
tasks already have rules and
deterministic processes to
solve and which
ones don't exist in our rules
registry so that that is where AI can
shine
right because if the reality is as I've
read I haven't personally
audited that a single query for you know
kind of an Enterprise mid Enterprise
company can cost a couple hundred
dollars to process
and
hallucinates is that really coste
efficient especially if there's a
deterministic solution out there that
works
100% and just to be clear on as much as
I think AI is amazing at certain tasks
this just um this just came across this
morning so I just want to put uh put it
up here I didn't believe it when someone
um posted this on Blue Sky um so I typed
it in myself it's not the exact same
wording but I got the exact same
result so then I'm like okay well is
this a Google thing or maybe it's like
what if I give it to
Claude so I gave this to Claude and and
asked you know is this correct and
Claude was like yeah no your no uh your
glass of water will not freeze at 27
degrees so I said but isn't 27 degrees
lower than 32 degrees and it said oh yes
expertise as far less infrastructure
think that like slapping on AI is going
to be safe and
reliable which leads me to another
question how do you even measure that so
if you look at chat bot Arena right I
have the name
right where you have two different llm
models and people are picking what they
prefer
okay a model has a referred
answer but
um different people in different context
with different language might have what
they call a preferred you know or a
correct answer and a preference is not
necessarily a
deterministic correct
answer okay I'm gonna um pause there
Daniel any any questions or should I
continue I I'm writing something things
down lot of cool points to discuss and
if anyone watching live wants to write
questions they can go for it continue
though okay good yeah I want this to be
interactive and not me just rambling on
so if you have anything anything think
you're curious about or not
so um what we're hoping to do is to
create a very basic protocol when I mean
protocol is a
guarantee if you're going to build these
types of systems just a simple
scaffolding of here are here is how you
do it and so what we need to do is have
our
intents predicted from our
words we need to reflect them back to
the
user so that we can see the intent of
the system I don't know if if rid's here
but she's the one that kind of like
she's amazing and she's the one that
kind of um introduced me to that idea
around how do we see into the mind of
our AI systems like what is the belief
of the system and I think if people are
concerned about the EU AI act that's
exactly what they want to be able to to
have is how much uncertainty exists in
your model uh and in your system right
because going back to that chatbot Ena
you might have preferences of model
answers but that is very different than
how efficient the system is at
completing a
task right like your model might have a
good answer but is it what the person
who's using the model needs to solve
their problem which is which is a much
different
Benchmark especially when you start
calculating the cost of running some of
these models
um secondly there's security
issues um but being able to configure
rules for these intents what is
deterministic and um what is
probabilistic
right and um there's one thing that kind
of shocked me whoops there's one thing
that kind of shocked me that um oh
because I'm in presenter mode I can't
move things around uh but I don't know
if you see here using
Claud the API I ran um crap my mouse
Wheels accidentally getting hit all the
time okay so if in running
pla there's a
um like 100% success rate if I ran it
through the user
interface but if I run it through the AP
and this is a benchmark of math word
problems that open AI released
the accuracy dropped to
30% why is that well it's
because the user interface when you use
the um the web app has all kinds of
fine-tuning that you and I have no idea
exist it's a black box
test
and when we run it through an API we
don't have the benefit of that and the
reason this is important is because when
I um and I'm going to stop sharing my
screen now when
I told my friend this who uses Claud on
a regular basis for data engineering
tasks he had no idea so he had no idea
he had to do all this extra because he's
like in the web UI it
works once I get it working in the web
UI why don't I just like you know
automated through
apis not necessarily Bo bother even
bothering to Benchmark it because he
trusted the web user
interface so I think that we're really
an immature kind of
industry um trying to apply AI to solve
really hard problems that often have
really significant safety compliance uh
uh
decisionmaking um impacts and I I don't
think we really have a a way
to understand how to design an engineer
trust uh and so that's that's what I'm
passionate about I just kind of wanted
to you know share with the community
some some of my research
and you know I think there's there's I
could ramble on here but I also don't
know if uh I'd like to like kind of take
a pause and see if if anyone has any
questions or
comments awesome I will read a question
from the live chat anyone else can write
and then I can make some other comments
and questions okay reconfigurability
trainer writes Ron did your work
building the architecture
include noncompliance related
performance kpis if so did anything
about that exercise surprise
you
noncompliance based
performance other API is not related to
system compliance got it so the if if
you haven't seen the the startup un
unifi.it down to three metrics you know
cost speed accuracy and you can test any
model and so I haven't used their
service
but they seem to have a really um good
way for you know as simple as possible
just simple API calls for people to test
various models various prompt
engineering various fine-tuning um for
benchmarking that has nothing to do with
compliance I think though there's a
disconnect for me around um I've worked
with some brilliant data scientists and
AI Engineers who you know working on
their Local Host local machine would
have incredible results and then they
good luck getting that into production
uh in the real world with like you know
uh outside of training uh I forgot the
the term but when you when you have
examples that are outside of your
training set
um and so that that just brings me back
to this idea
of benchmarking is absolutely important
for models 100 you know will not get me
to say anything else but like if you're
not
benchmarking in the real world how those
models are interacting
operationally and what the impact to the
business is
um you know eventually someone in the
finance department is going to is going
to be like hey we we just invested $5
million into Ai and like uh we have to
now have $3 million worth of extra HR
costs to maintain all these complex new
systems and you know our sales or
whatever our marketing we don't have any
real improvements
um I've been around to see those kinds
of layoffs they're not they're not fun
and so I I think that the discipline the
the business discipline um that a data
scientist could benefit from is is
really starting to include um thinking
about benchmarks Beyond simply you know
model performance or something like that
that's that's very interesting like to
kind of e Echo a piece back there within
a
compliance testing
sandbox skeleton or scaffold then other
kinds of measures and performances can
be evaluated but to
pursue those
measures
only when the the vector of the
performance isn't necessarily aligned
with that of the compliance then is
going to lead to some kind of go noo
with compliance down the road that might
not be trivial but if it was trivial
then it would have been trivial in any
order but in situations where it isn't
trivial then you want to make sure that
you have the expressivity to test
different compliance environments almost
before you test like the size of the
data for
example well you you brought up a really
important um point
um
so I'm not sure if people are familiar
with the whole world
models kind of buzz Yan leun if I'm
pronouncing his name right uh you know
he's been tweeting about posting you
know LinkedIn about it and um f f is it
f Lang I'm not sure if I'm pronouncing
her name right apologies um at Stanford
she just raised $200 million for her
startup on world models um
and there were a couple of things there
that I I just wanted to point out um the
first one
is when we have a simulator like a
physics simulator right so like um a car
driving simulator and we can run that
simulation a million times and then out
of that million times maybe we can do
some like you know deep learning on it
that is a fixed rule system right there
are there are rules just like we do in
compliance our simulators have things
they are physically bound to follow the
rules are known just like when you have
uh Alpha zero playing chess or go
whatever it is games are fixed rule
systems in the real
world in business the rules are
constantly changing legislation changes
the ways people operate changes HR rules
change language
changes there's no fixed simulator you
can have for a
business and so the the approach that
we're proposing with like this with
trust Loop protocol is to is to
say okay if we cannot impose some top-
down fixed rule
stimulator but we can create those
remember I had that image of the ants
trails that the if we can collect all
these like ant Trails for how things are
actually getting done what do people
mean by these uh you know different
words you can you can have a and I don't
know the actual technical term for this
but it's like a liquid simulator fluid
simul it's it's a it's revealing things
that are happening by these quasi rules
that are
emergent and that hopefully can create
World
models
um but not through a fixed system right
that was the first thing I wanted to say
before I go on to the second thing did
the answer did do that okay
um the second thing was I was lucky
enough to do this like little case study
for um Precision medicine department at
Stanford
um and they were doing a hackathon
around people who had rare diseases so
the Precision medicine um lab had very
few
patients but they had lots and lots and
lots of data I mean genomic data
proteomic data metabolomic like if you
name it they were just barraging them
with tests to create the most massive
data sets they could
on the few people they had with these
very rare diseases
and um to prepare for that hackathon I
met with another Stanford team that was
trying to create like the largest
physics data set in in the world uh I'm
wondering if they were actually part of
this F uh uh laying uh World model thing
but what was really interesting that
they did is they collected all this data
and then they ambigu everything to
numbers that you couldn't see what the
columns were
of the
data and I thought that was a really
interesting approach and so I asked the
organizer of the hackathon what you know
what was behind it and he goes because
we found when we have these data sets
with the words and the columns the
people who are experts right the trained
phds in their
field regularly
underperformed people who had no
knowledge or expertise of that field but
they were purely machine learning
experts and I thought that was um I
thought that was very interesting as
well that doesn't tie into the to the um
compliance thing but just this this idea
around um creating
simulators and removing even our own
language and constraints and how we
think
um and and just completely you know
trusting uh good
practices uh those seem to be the
highest
Benchmark um approaches at least talking
to you know an expert in the field that
created this massive physics data
set yeah in the design architecture you
outlined and kind of connecting it to
let's say um employee nestmate ants
leaving their traces through a Sandbox
or something like that it made me think
about the metacognitive environment that
cognitive tasks are performed in like if
the company were playing board
games which model or method should be
applied to each of the cognitive games
yeah and then the metacognitive task you
could bring out you know the heavy or
expensive one too often or you could
bring out the lightweight less perform
per one or narrower one too often so
that's like sort of thinking too much or
too little these kinds of metacognitive
or attentional tasks and it's almost
like okay over the last years we've
started to see the upswing of the
capacity of the sort of like horsepower
of the statistical probabilistic which
has always existed as this dual thread
along the more expert rule-based regular
expression type systems and then it's
like okay so we know at the very least
we have whether we think about it with
system one system two or you know
thinking symbolically and rule-based or
thinking probabilistically and and
numerically and then it's like now where
and how within an Enterprise auditing
and compliance environment that also
creates not just the required operations
that are that are needed but also the
training data where it's like what are
the low hanging fruit that we can use
the shorter ladder for what are the high
hanging fruit that like no one has been
able to hit what so what's our reach
goal it's like you know because we're
starting to see we have all these
different affordances to deploy that
have wildly different capacities and
different costs you could Outsource it
to someone for thousands of dollars over
weeks or we could do this for hundreds
of dollars over minutes and when you
burn through hundreds in just hitting
one query
those are critical and they really add
up yeah and that's I I kind of smiling
because I was just like you got it right
like that's exactly what we're trying to
architect here is when do you use AI
when
not which model which approach when do
you use an expert
system
um it's a really interesting problem
because if you're measuring against
operational performance versus is the
model
performance you might have very simple
hacks which are way cheaper to implement
faster to implement you know less it
complexity and you know and uh I I feel
like that is completely off the radar
right now right now because everyone's
like rushing towards this new
paradigm yeah not every company is a
frontier SL Foundation model
AI research
lab
so why use something more complex um
I'll read another question from the chat
and then any anyone else can write more
okay Andrew Pasa wrote nice talk all
relevant points topics on trust
regarding agent activity do you have an
opinion on the uses of actor critic
Frameworks in the case of llms for
output refinement fact checking Etc yeah
yeah great question um I think I heard
did he was the word expert in there or
opinion I'm not sure what it was let me
just say I just have an opinion I'm just
I am
just going through you know it's funny
because um writing a book or getting
published and now you get questions oh
like I have some secret answer no I'm
figuring all this out just like everyone
else um and I can tell you what I've
been
um interested in in where I think being
an author is awesome and where it sucks
so being where being an author is
awesome is that you're
completely removed from having to do any
of the work right like I got to spend
two years not coding and just thinking
about all these ideas and talking to the
most interesting people I could and you
know what about this what about this
right and so when we talk about these
agentic um actor
paradigms uh I I can share with you what
I've learned but it's not from a
practitioner point of view it is purely
from Reading thinking you know imagining
um and working on my own little kind of
agentic uh little
experiments so it's clearly very very
valuable I think for me personally just
even like through the chat UI for me to
write something and then you know CLA
would be like that's awesome that's
great and then you build it up and then
like I I'll send it in in a new chat and
I'll say okay now you're going to be the
role of a Critic tell me all the things
that's that's wrong right go through
that process and Andrew in actually a
friend uh a good friend um Yoshi he he
pointed me to a recent inuring um Talk
where he talks about the this emergence
of AI product managers and he talks
about this you know multi- um actor role
like you have the the first brainstorm
partner then the critic and then the you
know maybe the engineer who has to take
the critic and the bra and figure out a
builded you know and and like you can
see now in the like in the llm Chain of
Thought reasoning approaches they are
definitely you know they're even saying
like hey criticizing and reviewing Etc
so it's clearly a pattern that I think
has great value and is being engineered
and implemented um
however I I recently had an experience
with someone from the active inference
Institute I don't know if Lance is here
he's amazing I love him uh uh so
incredibly helpful
um I I recently worked on this paper the
first time I've ever submitted anything
for a you know talk um rld DM and
Ireland right uh reinforcement learning
multi- disciplinary um conference on
cognitive World models which is like how
do we take the world model approach
introduced in 2018 where you create a
simulation of a simulation super cool um
and now if we had trust Loop
protocol instead of a fixed rule
simulator we take this like emergent
kind of
data and I tried to write the paper
using kind of this actor approach right
I did my best and then I was like hey
before I submit to this conference I've
never written an academic paper before
don't have a PhD totally intimidated
help me great okay then I said please
critique it great you know improve it
and and I tried to go through that
multi-actor approach to using llm which
again I think is incredibly valuable
blah blah blah um and then I sent it to
Lance right someone who actually
does um who I trust deeply right there's
no better person other than car I can
think of right um and may ready right so
I he took a look at the paper and
immediately he's like it's missing boom
boom boom he's like you should try
asking chat GPT for help not knowing
that I was using quad like the whole
time and like it was really interesting
for me to see that despite using that
multiactor
approach it none of the things that
Lance pointed out did I get feedback
from those multi actors
um and I think that's how do you
Benchmark that right yeah that's that's
um awesome one one thought and I've seen
this also come up many many times is
like even when a character or a Persona
prompt layer is added so it's like okay
you know you're an engineer or you're a
product designer so so it's kind of
preempting trying to warm up or put
these uh general purpose models into
character in some sense the response
that that gets pinged back is always
going to have been like washed or
brought back towards the center of
gravity of this model that was trained
on prior text and so sometimes it's like
if somebody has three authentic ideas 1
2 3 and then they ask for it to be
upgraded and it looks on a first pass
like the professionalism has been
brought up greatly but at this point we
all know that we can get those kinds of
responses looking professional back
rapidly and maybe it converges to Common
idea 345 and if they had just sent the
authentic 123 with the typos and all
it's like we know that it could have we
could have added more and then also um
seeing what isn't there is very
different than just augmenting what is
there um I'll read a question from the
chat on this uh theme a little bit okay
reconfigurability trainer wrote what are
your expectations on how Legacy
Enterprise architecture will have to
change to adapt to AI how much it change
do firms have control over versus Locked
In by service
providers yeah I think this is the this
is like a critical critical point of
what I'm interested in with this
presentation today
is there's okay two layers to this the
first is a ton of working decades long
investment in infrastructure already
exists so the idea that you're going to
take decades worth of PDFs and data and
dump it all into a vector database and
do your prompt engineering and
fine-tuning uh and use that instead of
all these systems and investment that
work that's just insane to me I'm sorry
like
until we can show that Google can know
that 27 degrees is below 32 degrees
right like these are not trusted systems
they're probabilistic systems and the
the amount of
cost is just you know
outstanding uh out astounding sorry
numbers and so the idea and I know it's
like people want to learn these skills
you get a big pay jump if you have like
Lang chain and Vector DB and your you
know and everyone's starting from
scratch so you can become an expert
quickly um but there's already a ton of
infrastructure that works and so rather
than fir hosing everything through
AI um what's how do you control what is
AI and what is not like how does even
the business team decide what specific
data is going to be good and useful and
have an Roi to to use that right it just
it just feels like um uh it feels like
businesses feel so much pressure to
adopt this the the sea level has so much
pressure to show to shareholders here's
how we are GNA you know have Competitive
Edge and we're going to be a leader in
adopt AI they were like they haven't
like first really thought through some
of these questions and so I think the
exist leveraging existing infrastructure
is is the number one thing companies can
do is just like avoid AI when possible
Right but there are things that AI can
do that deterministic systems can't
which leads me to the other side of the
coin here which
is I've been in organizations that have
massive mean like half a million dollar
a year in like these data catalog and
you know data management systems and
like you talk to the Business Leaders or
the bi leaders
and and the data teams and like they
they're not even understanding each
other right the business people say oh
do this it seems so basic and then the
data teams they do all the stuff and
it's not matching
expectations and you know the data teams
are like we we're not mind readers for
what the business wants right and you so
the problem there is that the existing
infrastructure doesn't
work that's where I think AI can shine
that's where I think AI actually has an
incredible Advantage around when you
have all this inefficiency and getting
people to collaborate on it
infrastructure which is
deterministic that's where I think an
llm or something can unify people on
language and approaches in in intent
right so so I think that's it's a really
important question that um you just
highlighted I think these are some
key issues that that will that are that
are to live with um not to defeat
like if we equate determinism with
safety and probabilistic with danger
then we're not even going to get out of
bed in the morning like in cognitive
security we have one joke that the
safest airport is a parking lot you're
you're not going to have any issues with
the airplanes there but the the surfaces
and the processes that are being
actually done they they can't
be deterministically known ahead of time
right little motifs can and so obviously
again lwh hanging fruit yeah but then
understanding like everything is a a a
threshold of Tolerance there's always a
probabilistic um elements to Safety in
the real soft and and fuzzy world and so
understanding how all of these differ um
on one hand like constraints and
structures and formal language like what
is reasonable and all of this what is
risky and then on the other hand the the
the experiences in the actual
like what cognitive science is pointing
at yes people talk about affordances and
umelt and all these different aspects
that help us study it across different
systems but like just taking it to
people's day-to-days
experiences and what is um how do we
even accurately evaluate whether
something is too risky or not or what
these trade-offs are and um it's hard to
have situational
awareness it I'm I'm sure even without
knowing at the Enterprise scale because
it is like mapping intents preferences
what capacities and all these different
features again the kinds of things that
in cognitive science and active
inference we work on with the models
those are features in the world too and
how do we even know like where when how
what if
and it seems like now is the time to be
exploring in those
directions yeah yeah and and we're
almost at a at a time so I just want to
throw out there I I want to comment on
that in a second but just before I
forget um thank you all for anyone uh
who's who's uh shared your time with me
today um I definitely am looking to
connect with people in the active
inference Community whether it's just to
say hello if I want to meet people I
want to learn or if you're interested in
we're looking for a case study partner
um to basically try out the trust Loop
protocol to we know this talk has now
led to some conversations with investors
so if you want to connect please connect
because I'm I'm really excited about
this these problems um and I would like
to kind of leave on a on a note um
around
systems and um what you alluded to like
this real world emergent kind of um
situation we have in Enterprises um
there was a Santa Fe Institute talk I
don't know why I like ants I like ant so
um so they were talking about um the
efficiencies of like colonies and how
well they can adapt and learn and Sol
solve problems and the the one thing I
just it struck me that this the
scientists entire research came down to
like this one line and she said the
density of feedback loops in a system um
directly correlate to how quickly it can
adapt and learn and so the reason that
this protocol is called the trust Loop
protocol is because it's really a
ux kind of
interface um via just an
API to get that feedback across various
systems between probabilistic and
deterministic and blend them together
and um yeah I don't know is there any
anything else Daniel or uh is that how
do you feel about
I could make many comments on on ants
I'm I'm um what comes to mind is um over
the Decades of ants
research um people are trying to
understand like how do on every
continent except of course ironically
Antarctica how do these Collective
behavioral strategies work in all these
different niches with different
regularities so those are kind of like
different business operating
environments or like Market condition I
conditions or something like that and so
and there can be like multiple species
different strategies in the same Niche
so people have tried to apply all kinds
of different approaches and famously EO
Wilson promoted the cast ergonomic
hypothesis the idea that something like
an Adam Smith
1776 type story like free market in the
colony colonies that are better from
this economic perspective are are
maximizing the amount of income food you
know and outcome reproductively per unit
of biomass so that that's one view um
and that relates to like Optimal
foraging and a lot of other Concepts and
then as a contrasting voice to that sort
of economic
optimization researchers like my PhD
adviser Deborah Gordon
highlighted some things like you
mentioned such as the the rate and the
frequency of interactions the types of
interactions and learning and
developmental
trajectories
those capacities and those
patterns can dominate such that whatever
the economics are they sort of are
however they end up but they're being
driven by these micro level interactions
mhm and so it's like I when thinking
about businesses or other epistemic
environments um um just how two people
can look at the same Colony you know
same Institute same company whatever it
happens to be and both its viability
economically can be seen from that like
macroeconomic perspective otherwise it's
not going to persist but also the the
micro
interactions are the I mean if if um if
there's a great foraging plan but the
pherone evaporates too rapidly then it's
not going to work and so it's like where
are we at with digital cognitive or
knowledge work or information spaces
which is largely what we're talking
about including how those are
propagating
into physical spaces Logistics and
supply and all these different areas
physical spaces that have to information
space in influence them and then what
are going to be the sort of macro
structural properties of the system that
no nestmate could could grapple with and
then how is that going to relate to the
first person considerations like
accessibility felt sense of trust
cognitive
overhead all and and kind of like if
those can connect then there will be
at least local Harmony and
success but there's way more ways for
those not to connect way more
unsuccessful Collective behavioral
strategies than
successful and so in the digital space
where there's almost total degrees of
freedom of
design what does that interface look
like right and and and you're
approaching it and also what is that
it's like inter is all the way down
Market markof blankets all the way down
what is that interface between the
business intelligence and the API call
like all these different
connectors but if e if even one critical
one is not how it needs to be or not as
functional as it could
be that's what Improvement should seek
to Target and what proactive design
should should seek to
prevent hopefully we'll see this is also
new but I'm hoping if we can get a good
case
study then we should be able to quantif
quantify um some of these benchmarks
around connectivity through interfaces
through different systems across tasks
various models between deterministic and
probabilistic rules like that's that's
my next step I hope we can come up with
some
empirical evidence um what what zone
would the case study be and then how can
people contact you oh um so my email
address is Ron ran.com
um uh and the The Zone I don't know like
talking to the head of a hospital for
one possible case study um a couple of
incubators uh food industry I I don't
know like there's all kinds of
conversations until someone actually
signs an agreement right who knows
nothing may come out of it but I do
think we have a
compelling approach I think this is a
really hard expensive problem and if we
can find someone who's willing to give
us a chance just to
like
demonstrate as as you know I I guess you
know I understand it's an N of one right
but if we can
demonstrate
um that we can show we can show the I
want to use your language right the act
itself of making these connections
across various
interfaces just doing that can have
value right it's the digital equivalent
of pheromones right but that's that's
effectively what we're calling these
cognitive auditable cognitive Trails
it's just meant to say like we're
leaving these little paramone
drops creating a data set that then can
be handed over to a data science team to
analyze and hopefully come up with
insights um
yeah epic okay good luck Ron thank you
to all the live Chatters thank you for
presenting and looking forward to
learning more thank you so much everyone
byebye
bye for